2014年 在那个神奇的山东招远市
In 2014, in Zhao Yun City, China,
一家麦当劳成为了被监控拍下的top5哈人犯罪现场之一
the McDonald's became the scene of one of the most disturbing crimes caught on surveillance.
这是一场发生在家庭、孩子和顾客面前的血腥谋杀
A murder carried out in front of families, children, and customers.
而凶手们 则相信自己正在对抗“恶灵”
All by a group who believed they were fighting evil spirits.
那是5月28日 一个五指不见伸手的夜晚
It was the evening of May 28th.
37岁的吴硕艳是在一位在附近一家服装店工作的销售员
Wu Zhao Yun, 37 years old, a salesperson who worked at a nearby clothing store.
已经下班的她在麦当劳等着家人们的到来
After work, she was waiting at a McDonald's for her family to arrive.
大约晚上9点 六个人走了进来 包括五名成年人和一个少年
Around 9 pm, a group of six people entered, a mix of adults, and even one teenager.
但他们不是来点餐的
But they weren't there to order food.
他们是来传教的
Instead, they started preaching to customers, telling them about their religious beliefs.
但这还没完
But it didn't just stop there.
他们还要所有人的手机号码 声称他们将来还会联系
It began demanding everyone's cell phone numbers, claiming they needed them to future contact.
而当吴数次拒绝他们时 他们就开始向她发起攻击
And when Wu refused, not once, but twice, they turned on her.
这群人喊道 她是个恶魔
The group shouted that she was an evil spirit.
然后他们就开始在餐厅里所有人的面前攻击她
And then, in front of the entire restaurant, they began attacking her.
他们使用的武器包括椅子、拖把和他们的脚
Chairs, mops, and their feet.
这些动作毫不留情
The beating was merciless.
而任何试图干预的人则都受到了同样的威胁
And anyone who tried to intervene was threatened with the same fate.
而监控拍下了这一切
and the CCTV cameras recorded everything.
顾客们惊恐地不断后退 而吴则在众目睽睽之下被殴打致死
Customers backed away in fear as Wu was beaten to death and in full public view.
当警察到达时 他们逮捕了六名袭击者
When police finally arrived, they arrested all six attackers.
中国政府的通报称 凶手是“全能神”教会的成员
The Chinese government quickly reported that the killers were members of the Eastern Lightning cult.
这是一个备受争议的、根据基督教瞎编的教派
It's a controversial Christian-inspired sect.
该教派成立于1990年代 长期以来被国家列入邪教的清单
Found in the 1990s, which has been long accused by the state of being a dangerous cult.
全能神教会 是一个受基督教启发的团体 于1990年代在中国成立
Eastern Lightning, or the Church of Almighty God, is a Christian-inspired group founded in China in the 1990s.
据该团体的教典称 基督已经回归
According to the group, Christ is returned,
但祂以一位中国女性的形式出现 而他们的追随者必须接受他们的教义
but in the form of a Chinese woman, and their followers must embrace your teachings.
政府将其列为邪教
And the government labels this as an evil cult.
关键是 这个教派早就不是第一次出来跳了
And the thing is, this cult isn't even new to controversy.
多年来 当局指控“全能神”犯有强制改宗、财务剥削、家庭暴力和骚扰等罪行
Over the years, authorities have accused Eastern Lightning of forced conversations,
financial exploitation, domestic abuse, and harassment.
据报道 在一些农村地区
In some rural areas, reports say they apply high-pressure tactics on families to join or donate.
他们对家庭施加高压策略 要求他们加入或捐款
对于这次麦当劳杀人事件
In the context of the McDonald's killing,
官方声称那六名袭击者来自“全能神”内部的一个奇怪的分支
the official narrative claims that the six attackers came from a dissident or strange subgroup within Eastern Lightning.
他们可能不受教会中央的管理
Maybe not fully under the church's central control.
但他们的行为符合一些更激进的邪教信仰 比如将非信徒视为恶灵
But their actions align with some of the more radical cult beliefs, rejecting non-believers as evil spirits,
要求服从 如要求提供电话号码或联系方式
demanding submission, as in phone numbers or contact,
还有暴力地强制执行他们的教义
and enforcing their doctrine violently.
袭击者接受了审判
And the attackers were put on trial.
录像、证人和供词等都是判死他们的铁证
The footage, the witnesses, and the confessions all made it impossible to deny what happened.
团体中的两人 包括主犯 被判处死刑 并于2015年执行
Two of the group, including the ringleaders,
Senten to death and executed in 2015.
其他人则被判处长期监禁
The others received long prison sentences.
尘埃落定之后 这个案件成为了现代中国最臭名昭著的邪教犯罪
And in the aftermath, the case became one of the most infamous cult crimes in modern China.
它还导致了突袭、大规模逮捕和铁拳
It sparked raids, mass arrests, and a crackdown on the Church of Almighty God.
招远麦当劳命案至今仍是一个沉痛的警示
The Xiaoyan McDonald's murder remains a disturbing reminder
它向我们展示了信仰是如何走向狂热 并最终在最寻常不过的地方演变为骇人的暴力的
of how belief, worked into fanaticism, and erupted into violence, in the most ordinary places.
在这个案件中 监控捕捉到的不仅仅是图像
It's a case where surveillance didn't just capture an image.
它捕捉到的是一个意识形态 是一个模糊了信仰和妄想界限的信仰体系
It captured an entire ideology, a belief system that blurred the line between faith and delusion.
它还向世界展示了当一个团体认为自己的谋杀实为救赎时的恐怖
And it showed the world of how truly terrifying it is when a group convinces themselves that killing isn't murder, as salvation.